<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>current | Homepage</title>
    <link>https://www.raxlab.science/tag/current/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.raxlab.science/tag/current/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>current</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Rodrigo A. Carrasco, 2026</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.raxlab.science/images/icon_hu5d34eb5e588cdfdf4e24081213af8ad4_29191_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>current</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/tag/current/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>SAVIIA: Trusted Data Infrastructures for Field Science</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/project/saviia2025/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/project/saviia2025/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    From data capture to decision: SAVIIA links local orchestration with cloud pipelines and governance so that field data can be trusted, reused, and scaled.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-saviia&#34;&gt;What is SAVIIA?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SAVIIA&lt;/strong&gt; (Sistema de Administración y Visualización de Información para la Investigación y Análisis) is a &lt;strong&gt;trusted data infrastructure&lt;/strong&gt; for UC’s &lt;strong&gt;Regional Field Stations Network (RCER)&lt;/strong&gt;. It integrates &lt;strong&gt;scientific&lt;/strong&gt; (sensors, surveys, imagery) and &lt;strong&gt;operational&lt;/strong&gt; data (logistics, maintenance, safety) through a common governance model and &lt;strong&gt;hybrid local–cloud&lt;/strong&gt; architecture, enabling &lt;strong&gt;reproducible pipelines&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;auditable analyses&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;secure sharing&lt;/strong&gt; across teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-it-matters&#34;&gt;Why it matters&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Field research suffers from fragmented sources, intermittent connectivity, and uneven practices. SAVIIA addresses this by:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Standardizing&lt;/strong&gt; capture, metadata, and storage so datasets are &lt;strong&gt;FAIR&lt;/strong&gt; (findable, accessible, interoperable, reusable).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bridging&lt;/strong&gt; local constraints and cloud-scale analytics to support &lt;strong&gt;continuous, trustworthy&lt;/strong&gt; workflows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Connecting&lt;/strong&gt; scientific and operational streams to improve &lt;strong&gt;data quality, reproducibility&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;decision-making&lt;/strong&gt; in stations and partner projects.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;architecture-at-a-glance&#34;&gt;Architecture at a glance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local Orchestrator:&lt;/strong&gt; edge services for device/sensor ingestion, validation, caching, and scheduled exports; resilient to low/unstable connectivity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cloud Integration:&lt;/strong&gt; versioned data lake + workflow engine for ETL/ELT, quality checks, and lineage; analytical sandboxes for teams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shared Models &amp;amp; Views:&lt;/strong&gt; curated datasets, dashboards, and APIs for research, station operations, and stakeholders.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;data-governance&#34;&gt;Data governance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SAVIIA implements lightweight, enforceable rules centered on:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Quality:&lt;/strong&gt; schema checks, unit validation, completeness, timeliness SLAs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Traceability:&lt;/strong&gt; dataset identifiers, provenance, code–data–result linkage; reproducible notebooks/pipelines.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Access &amp;amp; Sharing:&lt;/strong&gt; roles, project spaces, embargo/visibility policies; clear licensing for reuse.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Safety &amp;amp; Ethics:&lt;/strong&gt; consent/acceptable-use registers; minimal exposure for sensitive fields.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-were-building-deliverables&#34;&gt;What we’re building (deliverables)&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SAVIIA Local&lt;/strong&gt;: deployable edge stack (ingestion, validation, scheduling, secure sync).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;SAVIIA Cloud&lt;/strong&gt;: data lake + workflow templates; metadata registry; dataset catalogue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Operations Kit&lt;/strong&gt;: runbooks, templates, QA playbooks, and “hello-station” examples.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visualization &amp;amp; APIs&lt;/strong&gt;: curated views and endpoints for research and station management.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Training &amp;amp; Onboarding&lt;/strong&gt;: short guides for station staff and researchers; governance checklists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SAVIIA advances the state of practice by &lt;strong&gt;operationalizing governance&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;linking edge capture with cloud analytics&lt;/strong&gt;, so field science can move from isolated datasets to &lt;strong&gt;reliable, decision-ready&lt;/strong&gt; evidence at scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project Team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Director: Rodrigo A. Carrasco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students: Sol Covacich, Pedro Zavala, Catalina Ortega&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PLASMA: Analytical Platform for Maintenance Systems</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2024plasma/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2024plasma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The PLASMA project aims to enhance maintenance management in industrial settings by developing a cloud-based analytical platform that integrates advanced predictive and prescriptive algorithms. Initially designed for use in complex systems like the ALMA Radiotelescope, these algorithms will now be adapted and validated for broader industrial applications. The platform’s core focus is to predict equipment degradation and remaining useful life (RUL), allowing maintenance teams to preemptively address issues and optimize resource allocation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with Viña Concha y Toro, PLASMA will deploy its algorithms within bottling and packaging lines to minimize operational disruptions and reduce the costs associated with equipment downtime. The project involves a comprehensive analysis of sensor data and production metrics to calibrate the predictive models for accuracy in real-world scenarios. Alongside prediction capabilities, the platform will also support decision-making through stochastic optimization models that balance maintenance costs with equipment reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project’s end goal is a scalable, cloud-based platform capable of managing predictive maintenance across diverse industrial sectors. With the support of technology partner Orión, PLASMA will be designed for 24/7 digital support, providing a robust solution for maintenance planning and execution. By ensuring the flexibility to adapt to various industrial contexts, the platform has the potential to generate significant value by reducing operational costs and enhancing equipment availability across sectors like viticulture, mining, and manufacturing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is funded by FONDEF IT24I0031 grant from ANID, and supported by Concha y Toro and Orion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project Team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Director: Alejandro Mac Cawley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subdirector: Rodrigo A. Carrasco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Researchers: Gonzalo Ruz, Margarita Castro, Anthony Cho&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Development of Oncology Waiting List Prioritization Strategies</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/project/polpub2024onco/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/project/polpub2024onco/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project focuses on improving access to cancer care in Chile by developing prioritization models for oncology waiting lists within the South Eastern Metropolitan Health Service. Cancer remains one of the leading causes of mortality in Chile, and the existing lack of standardized prioritization criteria has led to extensive and uneven waiting lists, particularly impacting disadvantaged socioeconomic groups. By enhancing the way oncology patients are prioritized for systemic therapies, such as chemotherapy, this project seeks to improve equity and efficiency within the public health system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our approach leverages data science and mathematical optimization to develop robust models for managing these waiting lists. The research involves a detailed mapping of current scheduling and prioritization processes for oncology treatments, which serves as the case study foundation. We will also conduct a comprehensive review of prioritization models in similar contexts to inform our methodology. Data quality assessments will allow us to identify actionable insights, and data extraction techniques will be applied to build effective decision-support tools based on available health data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through this project, we aim to create a framework for dynamic prioritization that can be tailored to capacity limitations and patient needs, incorporating constraints such as guaranteed health coverage and specific cancer treatment requirements. Beyond oncology, the methodologies and models developed here hold the potential for application in other areas of healthcare, providing a scalable solution for optimizing resource allocation and patient care across diverse medical fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is funded by Políticas Públicas UC grant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project Team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Director: Rodrigo A. Carrasco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Researchers: Jocelyn Dunstan, José Peña&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resource cost-aware scheduling problems under uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our project addresses the critical balance between resource consumption and scheduling efficiency in settings where resources are limited or costly, such as astronomical observatories, manufacturing, and maintenance processes. Managing these constraints effectively can lead to substantial performance improvements but requires advanced techniques to weigh the trade-off between consuming resources and meeting scheduling demands. In many cases, resources, such as energy or workforce, are not only limited but also costly, adding an extra layer of complexity to scheduling tasks optimally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A unique aspect of this research is its focus on scheduling under uncertainty, where key parameters, like job sizes or deadlines, may not be known beforehand. This complexity is particularly relevant to observatories in Chile, where variable factors such as sky quality or observation lengths affect task durations. Through collaboration with some of the largest observatories, we gain access to unique datasets and domain expertise, enabling us to test our methods in real-world scenarios. This approach also opens pathways to apply our findings in other industries that face similar scheduling and resource challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are developing a comprehensive set of prescriptive analytics tools, including new algorithms with strong theoretical guarantees and benchmarks that address these resource-cost-aware scheduling problems. Our work will involve constructing approximation algorithms using mathematical programming and resource augmentation techniques. We aim to build a publicly accessible repository of benchmark instances—using real-world data and factoring in uncertainties and various scheduling metrics—that will advance research in this field and provide robust, adaptable solutions for diverse applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is funded by FONDECYT 1231245 grant from ANID.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project Team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PI: Rodrigo A. Carrasco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Co-PI: Gonzalo Ruz&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Co-PI: Luis Aburto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Operations Research Tools Applied to Observatory Operations </title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/project/obervatoryops/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jul 2021 22:22:24 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/project/obervatoryops/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The problem of scheduling operations in astronomical observatories has been tackled in various ad-hoc ways. Although it is a central task in an observatory’s operation, which affects the utilization and throughput of observations, extensive manual intervention is still required in almost all observatories. Moreover, little resources have been invested in optimizing the scheduling’s efficiency, which, in the case of large-scale observatories like ALMA or VLT, might result in significant cost-effective improvements. This issue gains importance since observatory operations have increased in complexity, with plenty of sources of uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This issue has a lot in common with problems typically found in other industries. Operations research tools have been used here to develop solutions for many related topics, from scheduling production plans to routing delivery vehicles. These tools and methodologies have been a source of efficiency, allowing organizations to do more with limited resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project aims to connect these two worlds, kickstarting and fostering interdisciplinary research between operations research and astronomy operations by tackling one of the most relevant problems: optimal operations scheduling. The focus will be to develop and apply operations research tools to construct decision support systems that can help managers improve efficiency and utilization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is funded by grant ASTRO20-0058 from ANID and the Atacama Large Millimeter Array (ALMA) Radio Telescope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project Team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lead Researcher: Rodrigo A. Carrasco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Associate Researchers: Andrés Jordán, Vincent Suc, Rafael Brahm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engineers: Benjamín Bastidas, Constanza Lorca&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students: Looking for motivated students to work in this topic!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prescriptive Maintenance</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/project/faultdetection/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 22:22:45 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/project/faultdetection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project has two main lines of research. In one, we are developing tools to detect and diagnose faults in an automatic fashion. Using machine learning and mathematical modeling techniques, we are developing algorithms to help in online deteccion of faults at the ALMA Radiotelescope. In a second line, we are developing decision support tools, based on stochastic optimization, to develop robust maintenance plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work is partially funded by FIE-2016-V022 and 16IFI6626 CORFO Grants.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
