<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Alejandro Mac Cawley | Homepage</title>
    <link>https://www.raxlab.science/author/alejandro-mac-cawley/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.raxlab.science/author/alejandro-mac-cawley/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Alejandro Mac Cawley</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Rodrigo A. Carrasco, 2025</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 08:30:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.raxlab.science/author/alejandro-mac-cawley/avatar_hu2e16297ecf7ac2892b5658f789c3a946_15529_270x270_fill_q90_lanczos_center.jpg</url>
      <title>Alejandro Mac Cawley</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/author/alejandro-mac-cawley/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>XV Chilean Conference on Operations Research</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/251130-optima/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/251130-optima/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At &lt;strong&gt;OPTIMA 2025 (XV Chilean Conference on Operations Research)&lt;/strong&gt;, our group shared three contributions spanning healthcare operations, log analytics for observatory systems, and industrial maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diego San Martín&lt;/strong&gt; presented a robust routing framework for home hospitalization with interdisciplinary teams, addressing uncertainty in demand and travel times while balancing workload and service levels. This work is part of our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FONDECYT project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; co-authored with Rodrigo A. Carrasco.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Andrés Catalán&lt;/strong&gt; introduced a decision-oriented system relevance ranking for log analysis at ESO’s Paranal Observatory using an extended MULTIMOORA approach, supporting maintenance triage from high-volume operational logs. This work is part of our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FONDECYT project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with Rodrigo A. Carrasco and Gonzalo Ruz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alejandro Mac-Cawley&lt;/strong&gt; presented a study on predicting equipment degradation in wine bottling lines from sensor data (with T. Stuck, R. Askenasy, R. Carrasco-Schmidt, M. Castro, A. Cho, R. Luna, and G. Ruz). This contribution is part of the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2024plasma/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PLASMA project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in collaboration with Viña Concha y Toro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together, these talks underline our focus on applying rigorous operations research and data-driven methods to real-world challenges in health services, large-scale technical systems, and industrial operations—advancing the impact of our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/&#34;&gt;FONDECYT&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2024plasma/&#34;&gt;PLASMA&lt;/a&gt; lines across domains.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13th International Conference on Mathematical Methods in Reliability</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250626-mmr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250626-mmr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At &lt;strong&gt;MMR 2025&lt;/strong&gt;, our group contributed three presentations that reflect the breadth of our work at the intersection of data science, optimization, and maintenance engineering across diverse industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ignacio Riego&lt;/strong&gt; presented a data-driven solution for &lt;strong&gt;automated maintenance planning in the airline industry&lt;/strong&gt;, focusing on the creation of personalized maintenance checks. This work is part of our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FONDECYT project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which explores optimization and analytics strategies to improve large-scale maintenance operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Andrés Catalán&lt;/strong&gt; shared a novel method for &lt;strong&gt;log anomaly detection in distributed systems&lt;/strong&gt;. His talk introduced a transformer-based approach combining sentiment analysis and explainability to enhance detection in complex environments. This research is also embedded within the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FONDECYT project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, addressing predictive modeling in high-frequency operational contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alejandro Maccawley and Ricardo Askenazy&lt;/strong&gt; presented a predictive model for &lt;strong&gt;equipment degradation in wine bottling lines&lt;/strong&gt;, using real-time sensor data to anticipate failures and optimize interventions. This work is part of the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2024plasma/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PLASMA project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a collaboration with Viña Concha y Toro focused on applying prescriptive maintenance tools in the food and beverage sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together, these talks demonstrate the versatility of our research group in applying cutting-edge analytical methods to real-world maintenance challenges, and the relevance of our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/&#34;&gt;FONDECYT&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2024plasma/&#34;&gt;PLASMA&lt;/a&gt; initiatives in advancing applied research across industries.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PLASMA: Analytical Platform for Maintenance Systems</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2024plasma/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2024plasma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The PLASMA project aims to enhance maintenance management in industrial settings by developing a cloud-based analytical platform that integrates advanced predictive and prescriptive algorithms. Initially designed for use in complex systems like the ALMA Radiotelescope, these algorithms will now be adapted and validated for broader industrial applications. The platform’s core focus is to predict equipment degradation and remaining useful life (RUL), allowing maintenance teams to preemptively address issues and optimize resource allocation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with Viña Concha y Toro, PLASMA will deploy its algorithms within bottling and packaging lines to minimize operational disruptions and reduce the costs associated with equipment downtime. The project involves a comprehensive analysis of sensor data and production metrics to calibrate the predictive models for accuracy in real-world scenarios. Alongside prediction capabilities, the platform will also support decision-making through stochastic optimization models that balance maintenance costs with equipment reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project’s end goal is a scalable, cloud-based platform capable of managing predictive maintenance across diverse industrial sectors. With the support of technology partner Orión, PLASMA will be designed for 24/7 digital support, providing a robust solution for maintenance planning and execution. By ensuring the flexibility to adapt to various industrial contexts, the platform has the potential to generate significant value by reducing operational costs and enhancing equipment availability across sectors like viticulture, mining, and manufacturing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is funded by FONDEF IT24I0031 grant from ANID, and supported by Concha y Toro and Orion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project Team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Director: Alejandro Mac Cawley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subdirector: Rodrigo A. Carrasco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Researchers: Gonzalo Ruz, Margarita Castro, Anthony Cho&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
