<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>interview | Homepage</title>
    <link>https://www.raxlab.science/tag/interview/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.raxlab.science/tag/interview/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>interview</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Rodrigo A. Carrasco, 2025</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 10:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.raxlab.science/images/icon_hu5d34eb5e588cdfdf4e24081213af8ad4_29191_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>interview</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/tag/interview/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>La Florida Hospital Triples Oncology Appointments through Use of Data Science</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250730-emol/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250730-emol/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This interview, published in &lt;em&gt;El Mercurio&lt;/em&gt;, highlights the results of an innovative pilot program that &lt;strong&gt;tripled oncology care capacity&lt;/strong&gt; at Hospital Dra. Eloísa Díaz de La Florida. The project combined &lt;strong&gt;data science&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;process redesign&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;natural language processing&lt;/strong&gt; to transform scattered patient data into structured information for clinical management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I discussed how our team—together with &lt;strong&gt;José Peña&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Jocelyn Dunstan&lt;/strong&gt;, and professionals from the Hospital de La Florida, developed a model that automates patient tracking, identifies care bottlenecks, and improves prioritization. By integrating data across systems, the pilot helped increase the number of patients managed from 900 to nearly 3,000 per care navigator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initiative demonstrates how &lt;strong&gt;algorithmic tools can support, not replace, clinical judgment&lt;/strong&gt;, and how innovation, when designed with system constraints in mind, can have immediate and scalable impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;📰 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ing.uc.cl/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/6067186_4469944-scaled.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the article (image)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Radio Interview: Managing Cancer Patient Pathways through Data</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250728-biobio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250728-biobio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With &lt;strong&gt;José Peña&lt;/strong&gt; we were interviewed on &lt;strong&gt;Radio BioBio&lt;/strong&gt; to discuss our research on oncology patient management, carried out in collaboration with &lt;strong&gt;José Peña&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Jocelyn Dunstan&lt;/strong&gt;. The conversation focused on how many cancer patients in Chile face fragmented care and long delays, and how we can use data science, natural language processing, and optimization tools to support more equitable and timely care pathways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We emphasized that patients should not have to navigate complex systems alone—and that we can use algorithmic tools not to replace human judgment, but to strengthen it. As I said during the interview: &lt;em&gt;“The goal is to put intelligence at the service of life.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;▶️ 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.instagram.com/reel/DMjGlCLIPAx/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Watch the summary clip on Instagram&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algorithms in a hyperconnected world</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/240513-13c/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/240513-13c/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
