<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Gonzalo Ruz | Homepage</title>
    <link>https://www.raxlab.science/author/gonzalo-ruz/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.raxlab.science/author/gonzalo-ruz/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Gonzalo Ruz</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Rodrigo A. Carrasco, 2025</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.raxlab.science/author/gonzalo-ruz/avatar_hucee97c335a1fd77d7fb9d084f25b14c0_30633_270x270_fill_q90_lanczos_center.jpg</url>
      <title>Gonzalo Ruz</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/author/gonzalo-ruz/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>PLASMA: Analytical Platform for Maintenance Systems</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2024plasma/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2024plasma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The PLASMA project aims to enhance maintenance management in industrial settings by developing a cloud-based analytical platform that integrates advanced predictive and prescriptive algorithms. Initially designed for use in complex systems like the ALMA Radiotelescope, these algorithms will now be adapted and validated for broader industrial applications. The platform’s core focus is to predict equipment degradation and remaining useful life (RUL), allowing maintenance teams to preemptively address issues and optimize resource allocation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with Viña Concha y Toro, PLASMA will deploy its algorithms within bottling and packaging lines to minimize operational disruptions and reduce the costs associated with equipment downtime. The project involves a comprehensive analysis of sensor data and production metrics to calibrate the predictive models for accuracy in real-world scenarios. Alongside prediction capabilities, the platform will also support decision-making through stochastic optimization models that balance maintenance costs with equipment reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project’s end goal is a scalable, cloud-based platform capable of managing predictive maintenance across diverse industrial sectors. With the support of technology partner Orión, PLASMA will be designed for 24/7 digital support, providing a robust solution for maintenance planning and execution. By ensuring the flexibility to adapt to various industrial contexts, the platform has the potential to generate significant value by reducing operational costs and enhancing equipment availability across sectors like viticulture, mining, and manufacturing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is funded by FONDEF IT24I0031 grant from ANID, and supported by Concha y Toro and Orion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project Team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Director: Alejandro Mac Cawley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subdirector: Rodrigo A. Carrasco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Researchers: Gonzalo Ruz, Margarita Castro, Anthony Cho&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resource cost-aware scheduling problems under uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our project addresses the critical balance between resource consumption and scheduling efficiency in settings where resources are limited or costly, such as astronomical observatories, manufacturing, and maintenance processes. Managing these constraints effectively can lead to substantial performance improvements but requires advanced techniques to weigh the trade-off between consuming resources and meeting scheduling demands. In many cases, resources, such as energy or workforce, are not only limited but also costly, adding an extra layer of complexity to scheduling tasks optimally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A unique aspect of this research is its focus on scheduling under uncertainty, where key parameters, like job sizes or deadlines, may not be known beforehand. This complexity is particularly relevant to observatories in Chile, where variable factors such as sky quality or observation lengths affect task durations. Through collaboration with some of the largest observatories, we gain access to unique datasets and domain expertise, enabling us to test our methods in real-world scenarios. This approach also opens pathways to apply our findings in other industries that face similar scheduling and resource challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are developing a comprehensive set of prescriptive analytics tools, including new algorithms with strong theoretical guarantees and benchmarks that address these resource-cost-aware scheduling problems. Our work will involve constructing approximation algorithms using mathematical programming and resource augmentation techniques. We aim to build a publicly accessible repository of benchmark instances—using real-world data and factoring in uncertainties and various scheduling metrics—that will advance research in this field and provide robust, adaptable solutions for diverse applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is funded by FONDECYT 1231245 grant from ANID.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project Team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PI: Rodrigo A. Carrasco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Co-PI: Gonzalo Ruz&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Co-PI: Luis Aburto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A RUL Estimation System from Clustered Run-to-Failure Degradation Signals</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/cho-2022-rul-sensors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/cho-2022-rul-sensors/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving prescriptive maintenance by incorporating post-prognostic information through chance constraints</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/cho-2022-prmain-ieeeaccess/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/cho-2022-prmain-ieeeaccess/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slow Degradation Fault Detection in a Harsh Environment</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/cho-2020-fdd-ieeeaccess/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/cho-2020-fdd-ieeeaccess/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GEMS: variable-Generation Energy Management with Storage</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2020gema/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 22:25:44 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2020gema/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the exciting topics we&amp;rsquo;ve been working on is algorithms and models related to energy management, where uncertainty is a crucial element in the process. In particular, our focus is on building decision support tools for optimal storage management when a variable and intermittent energy source is used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project combines machine learning methodologies and stochastic optimization tools to develop optimal energy management systems for a system with photovoltaic generation, interconnection with the grid, and energy storage. If no storage is available, the decision is simple: if the generation is larger than our demand, we sell to the grid. Otherwise, we need to buy from the grid. However, when storage is present, the decision is more complex. Should we store the energy for future usage? Or maybe tomorrow, we will have a large surplus of energy that allows us to use the energy today, at a time when the price is high. When is the best time to sell, store, or use solar energy? We answer these questions through our research project by developing a prototype that implements the optimal decisions defined by our mathematical optimization models and measuring this approach&amp;rsquo;s benefits compared to today&amp;rsquo;s standard storage policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is funded by FONDEF ID19I10158 grant from ANID y has cloud resources thanks to the AWS Cloud Credit for Research program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project Team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PI/Director: Rodrigo A. Carrasco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subdirector: Tito Homem-de-Mello&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Researchers: Francisco Jara, Jocelyn Olivari, Gonzalo Ruz, Carlos Silva&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engineers: Benjamín Bastidas, José Luis Ortiz&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students: Anthony D. Cho, Helena García, César Cerda&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prescriptive Maintenance</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/project/faultdetection/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 22:22:45 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/project/faultdetection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project has two main lines of research. In one, we are developing tools to detect and diagnose faults in an automatic fashion. Using machine learning and mathematical modeling techniques, we are developing algorithms to help in online deteccion of faults at the ALMA Radiotelescope. In a second line, we are developing decision support tools, based on stochastic optimization, to develop robust maintenance plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work is partially funded by FIE-2016-V022 and 16IFI6626 CORFO Grants.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
