<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>analytics | Homepage</title>
    <link>https://www.raxlab.science/tag/analytics/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.raxlab.science/tag/analytics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>analytics</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Rodrigo A. Carrasco, 2025</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 08:30:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.raxlab.science/images/icon_hu5d34eb5e588cdfdf4e24081213af8ad4_29191_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>analytics</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/tag/analytics/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>XV Chilean Conference on Operations Research</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/251130-optima/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/251130-optima/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At &lt;strong&gt;OPTIMA 2025 (XV Chilean Conference on Operations Research)&lt;/strong&gt;, our group shared three contributions spanning healthcare operations, log analytics for observatory systems, and industrial maintenance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diego San Martín&lt;/strong&gt; presented a robust routing framework for home hospitalization with interdisciplinary teams, addressing uncertainty in demand and travel times while balancing workload and service levels. This work is part of our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FONDECYT project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; co-authored with Rodrigo A. Carrasco.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Andrés Catalán&lt;/strong&gt; introduced a decision-oriented system relevance ranking for log analysis at ESO’s Paranal Observatory using an extended MULTIMOORA approach, supporting maintenance triage from high-volume operational logs. This work is part of our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FONDECYT project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; with Rodrigo A. Carrasco and Gonzalo Ruz.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alejandro Mac-Cawley&lt;/strong&gt; presented a study on predicting equipment degradation in wine bottling lines from sensor data (with T. Stuck, R. Askenasy, R. Carrasco-Schmidt, M. Castro, A. Cho, R. Luna, and G. Ruz). This contribution is part of the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2024plasma/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PLASMA project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; in collaboration with Viña Concha y Toro.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together, these talks underline our focus on applying rigorous operations research and data-driven methods to real-world challenges in health services, large-scale technical systems, and industrial operations—advancing the impact of our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/&#34;&gt;FONDECYT&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2024plasma/&#34;&gt;PLASMA&lt;/a&gt; lines across domains.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IND3750 Gestión de Operaciones Avanzada</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/post/teaching/ind3750-gesopavz/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Oct 2025 00:00:00 -0300</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/post/teaching/ind3750-gesopavz/</guid>
      <description>&lt;div class=&#34;alert alert-note&#34;&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
    La gestión es el puente entre los datos y la decisión: donde las hipótesis se encuentran con las restricciones, y la evidencia se convierte en acción.
  &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En un entorno de incertidumbre y cambio tecnológico acelerado, las operaciones requieren criterio más que recetas. Este curso invita a mirar con lupa las herramientas de OR, analítica e IA, evaluando cuándo funcionan, por qué, y con qué gobernanza pueden escalar en organizaciones reales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IND3750&lt;/strong&gt; es un curso del &lt;strong&gt;Magíster en Ingeniería Industrial (MII)&lt;/strong&gt; orientado a revisar, con mirada crítica, desarrollos avanzados en &lt;strong&gt;Gestión de Operaciones&lt;/strong&gt;: optimización, cadenas de suministro, variabilidad e incertidumbre, &lt;em&gt;lean production&lt;/em&gt;, y el impacto reciente de &lt;strong&gt;analytics&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;big data&lt;/strong&gt; y &lt;strong&gt;IA&lt;/strong&gt; en la disciplina. El foco está en &lt;strong&gt;entender límites y supuestos&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;evaluar evidencia&lt;/strong&gt; y &lt;strong&gt;dimensionar condiciones de uso&lt;/strong&gt; en organizaciones reales.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;-por-qué-este-curso-es-clave-en-el-mii&#34;&gt;🎓 ¿Por qué este curso es clave en el MII?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hoy, la complejidad de las operaciones requiere el apoyo de herramientas cuantitativas más sofisticadas. Pero en ese contexto es importante reconocer las limitaciones y ser críticos de cómo se pueden usar y el valor que generan, aprendiendo a reconocer su importancia y aplicabilidad. Es un ramo importante pues:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pasar del paper al impacto exige &lt;strong&gt;pensamiento crítico&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;validación rigurosa&lt;/strong&gt; y &lt;strong&gt;gobernanza de datos&lt;/strong&gt; (calidad, trazabilidad, oportunidad).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;La toma de decisiones en operaciones implica &lt;strong&gt;incertidumbre&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;recursos limitados&lt;/strong&gt; y &lt;strong&gt;trade-offs&lt;/strong&gt; entre costo, servicio, riesgo y sostenibilidad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Los modelos (OR/ML/IA) solo generan valor si están &lt;strong&gt;correctamente especificados&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;bien evaluados&lt;/strong&gt; (in/out-of-sample, ablation, contrafactual) y &lt;strong&gt;alineados con procesos y personas&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Formar líderes del MII implica &lt;strong&gt;defender decisiones auditables y explicables&lt;/strong&gt;, con métricas de impacto y criterios de transferencia.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;En pocas palabras, habilita a los estudiantes para identificar cómo encontrar herramientas avanzadas de gestión de operaciones y aplicarlas a sus organizaciones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;-contenidos-del-curso&#34;&gt;🧭 Contenidos del curso&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;El curso se organiza en los siguientes módulos principales:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Estrategia y coordinación de operaciones&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gestión de la cadena de abastecimiento y coordinación a nivel organizacional.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Optimización de procesos y planificación de recursos con enfoque de negocio.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Principios de Lean Production y su impacto en desempeño operacional.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;2&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Variabilidad, incertidumbre y decisión&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Modelamiento de la variabilidad y toma de decisiones bajo incertidumbre.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gestión de inventarios y logística en contextos de alta complejidad.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Aplicaciones comparadas en manufactura, servicios y comercio electrónico.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;ol start=&#34;3&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Analytics e Industria 4.0&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Integración de investigación de operaciones con ciencia de datos y analítica avanzada.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Uso de Big Data, Machine Learning e IA en gestión moderna de operaciones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Revisión crítica de literatura y casos para implementar soluciones basadas en datos.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;-libros-recomendados&#34;&gt;📘 Libros recomendados&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A continuación encontrarás una selección de libros especialmente útiles para complementar el aprendizaje en este curso. Se incluyen textos guía y referencias adicionales que destacan por su claridad, enfoque aplicado o profundidad teórica. Cada título viene con un enlace afiliado directo a Amazon para adquirirlo, o a su fuente gratuita si corresponde.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-texto-guía&#34;&gt;🔹 Texto guía&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Jacobs, F. R., &amp;amp; Chase, R. B. (2023). &lt;em&gt;Operations and Supply Chain Management&lt;/em&gt; (17th Edition). McGraw-Hill.&lt;br&gt;
Texto actualizado que cubre de manera integral la gestión de operaciones y cadenas de suministro, con un enfoque en aplicaciones prácticas y casos globales.&lt;br&gt;
👉 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.to/3HD3TcY&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ver en Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;-textos-adicionales&#34;&gt;🔸 Textos adicionales&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cachon, G., &amp;amp; Terwiesch, C. (2021). &lt;em&gt;Matching Supply with Demand: An Introduction to Operations Management&lt;/em&gt; (4th Edition). McGraw-Hill.&lt;br&gt;
Una introducción clara y aplicada a la gestión de operaciones, centrada en el equilibrio entre oferta y demanda, con ejemplos prácticos y casos de estudio.&lt;br&gt;
👉 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.to/4ltSJFn&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ver en Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stevenson, W. J. (2020). &lt;em&gt;Operations Management&lt;/em&gt; (14th Edition). McGraw-Hill.&lt;br&gt;
Texto ampliamente utilizado que cubre de manera integral los fundamentos de la gestión de operaciones, con ejemplos prácticos y aplicaciones en diversos sectores.&lt;br&gt;
👉 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.to/474mnxC&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ver en Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cathy O’Neil (2016) – &lt;em&gt;Weapons of Math Destruction: How Big Data Increases Inequality and Threatens Democracy&lt;/em&gt;. Crown Books.&lt;br&gt;
Un ensayo crítico sobre el impacto negativo de modelos mal diseñados.&lt;br&gt;
👉 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://amzn.to/3IfneRx&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ver en Amazon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;-proyectos-relacionados&#34;&gt;🔗 Proyectos relacionados&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Este curso se conecta con investigaciones aplicadas que hemos desarrollado:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2020gema/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;📄 Optimización estocástica para la gestión de energía&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;📦 Modelos de optimización para planificación estratégica y operativa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/polpub2024onco/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;🏥 Planificación y priorización de listas de espera oncológicas&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Este curso avanza el conocimiento en Gestión de Operaciones al &lt;strong&gt;integrar teoría de alto nivel con evaluación empírica y criterios de transferencia&lt;/strong&gt;, formando profesionales capaces de &lt;strong&gt;conectar datos, modelos y procesos&lt;/strong&gt; para tomar &lt;strong&gt;decisiones defendibles&lt;/strong&gt; que generen impacto real en sus organizaciones.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leading with Evidence in Times of Uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/251007-emol/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/251007-emol/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This opinion column, published in &lt;em&gt;El Mercurio&lt;/em&gt;, argues that the &lt;strong&gt;value&lt;/strong&gt; of data work is realized in the prescriptive step: turning predictions into feasible actions under real-world constraints—“the predictive informs; the prescriptive decides.” It lays out what’s required to make that leap: rigorous data governance (quality, traceability, timeliness), explicit treatment of uncertainty (scenarios and robust optimization), short-cycle impact metrics, and decision governance (clear activation rules and explainability). Drawing on examples in health, environmental monitoring, and maintenance, it proposes a practical path: start from high-value problems, set honest baselines, formulate prescriptive models with actual constraints, pilot with counterfactual evaluation, and then institutionalize and scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;📰 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ingenieriaindustrial.ing.uc.cl/blog/liderar-con-evidencia-en-tiempos-de-incertidumbre/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Artificial City: Designing Future Scenarios through Data and AI</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250911-planeo/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250911-planeo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;TIn this interview with &lt;em&gt;Revista PLANEO&lt;/em&gt;, I discuss how data science can inform urban decision-making under uncertainty, bridging descriptive, predictive, and prescriptive analytics, while stressing governance, institutional capacity, and ethics. We talk about translating complex models into actionable tools for public decision-makers, the need for data literacy and transparent communication, and the risk of widening gaps if only wealthy cities can leverage data. I argue for shared repositories and collaboration mechanisms so that smaller or vulnerable municipalities can benefit as well, advancing fairer and more sustainable urban management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The challenge is to prevent only the wealthiest cities from benefiting from the use of data… we need collaboration mechanisms and shared repositories…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;📰 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://revistaplaneo.cl/2025/09/09/entrevista-a-rodrigo-carrasco-el-desafio-es-evitar-que-solo-las-ciudades-mas-ricas-puedan-beneficiarse-del-uso-de-datos-necesitamos-mecanismos-de-colaboracion-y-repositorios-compartidos-que-permit/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>La Florida Hospital Triples Oncology Appointments through Use of Data Science</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250730-emol/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250730-emol/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This interview, published in &lt;em&gt;El Mercurio&lt;/em&gt;, highlights the results of an innovative pilot program that &lt;strong&gt;tripled oncology care capacity&lt;/strong&gt; at Hospital Dra. Eloísa Díaz de La Florida. The project combined &lt;strong&gt;data science&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;process redesign&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;natural language processing&lt;/strong&gt; to transform scattered patient data into structured information for clinical management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I discussed how our team—together with &lt;strong&gt;José Peña&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Jocelyn Dunstan&lt;/strong&gt;, and professionals from the Hospital de La Florida, developed a model that automates patient tracking, identifies care bottlenecks, and improves prioritization. By integrating data across systems, the pilot helped increase the number of patients managed from 900 to nearly 3,000 per care navigator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initiative demonstrates how &lt;strong&gt;algorithmic tools can support, not replace, clinical judgment&lt;/strong&gt;, and how innovation, when designed with system constraints in mind, can have immediate and scalable impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;📰 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ing.uc.cl/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/6067186_4469944-scaled.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the article (image)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Radio Interview: Managing Cancer Patient Pathways through Data</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250728-biobio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250728-biobio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With &lt;strong&gt;José Peña&lt;/strong&gt; we were interviewed on &lt;strong&gt;Radio BioBio&lt;/strong&gt; to discuss our research on oncology patient management, carried out in collaboration with &lt;strong&gt;José Peña&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Jocelyn Dunstan&lt;/strong&gt;. The conversation focused on how many cancer patients in Chile face fragmented care and long delays, and how we can use data science, natural language processing, and optimization tools to support more equitable and timely care pathways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We emphasized that patients should not have to navigate complex systems alone—and that we can use algorithmic tools not to replace human judgment, but to strengthen it. As I said during the interview: &lt;em&gt;“The goal is to put intelligence at the service of life.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;▶️ 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.instagram.com/reel/DMjGlCLIPAx/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Watch the summary clip on Instagram&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13th International Conference on Mathematical Methods in Reliability</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250626-mmr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250626-mmr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At &lt;strong&gt;MMR 2025&lt;/strong&gt;, our group contributed three presentations that reflect the breadth of our work at the intersection of data science, optimization, and maintenance engineering across diverse industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ignacio Riego&lt;/strong&gt; presented a data-driven solution for &lt;strong&gt;automated maintenance planning in the airline industry&lt;/strong&gt;, focusing on the creation of personalized maintenance checks. This work is part of our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FONDECYT project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which explores optimization and analytics strategies to improve large-scale maintenance operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Andrés Catalán&lt;/strong&gt; shared a novel method for &lt;strong&gt;log anomaly detection in distributed systems&lt;/strong&gt;. His talk introduced a transformer-based approach combining sentiment analysis and explainability to enhance detection in complex environments. This research is also embedded within the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FONDECYT project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, addressing predictive modeling in high-frequency operational contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alejandro Maccawley and Ricardo Askenazy&lt;/strong&gt; presented a predictive model for &lt;strong&gt;equipment degradation in wine bottling lines&lt;/strong&gt;, using real-time sensor data to anticipate failures and optimize interventions. This work is part of the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2024plasma/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PLASMA project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a collaboration with Viña Concha y Toro focused on applying prescriptive maintenance tools in the food and beverage sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together, these talks demonstrate the versatility of our research group in applying cutting-edge analytical methods to real-world maintenance challenges, and the relevance of our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/&#34;&gt;FONDECYT&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2024plasma/&#34;&gt;PLASMA&lt;/a&gt; initiatives in advancing applied research across industries.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joining prediction and optimization: prescriptive scenario generation for energy management with storage </title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250325-heidelberg/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250325-heidelberg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the &lt;strong&gt;1st Heidelberg–Chile Workshop on Scientific Computing&lt;/strong&gt;, I presented our research on prescriptive scenario generation for energy management in microgrids with renewable generation and battery storage. The talk focused on bridging the gap between prediction and optimization by integrating forecasting methods and scenario-based stochastic programming into a unified decision-making framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We explored techniques for generating decision-aware scenarios using adaptive partitioning methods and highlighted the shift from a “predict-then-optimize” approach to a “predict-and-optimize” paradigm. Results from simulation studies in residential microgrids demonstrated significant gains in operational efficiency compared to conventional control strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work is part of the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2020gema/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GEMA project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, funded by FONDEF, and involves collaboration with colleagues and students across several institutions. The methods developed are currently being tested in real-world pilot implementations and cloud-based energy platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When Time Is Life: Innovation for Oncology Waitlists in Chile</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250312-polpub/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250312-polpub/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 12, 2025, I published an opinion piece in &lt;em&gt;El País&lt;/em&gt; titled &lt;em&gt;“When Time Is Life: Innovation for Oncology Waiting Lists in Chile.”&lt;/em&gt; The article discusses how data-driven innovation can transform oncology waitlist management, reducing delays and improving access to timely care. It highlights key strategies—such as digitalization, automation, and optimization—to enhance both efficiency and equity in the Chilean healthcare system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read the full article here: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://elpais.com/chile/2025-03-12/cuando-el-tiempo-es-vida-innovacion-para-las-listas-de-espera-oncologicas-en-chile.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;El País&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oncology Waitlist: Strategies for Management in Health Services</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/241120-polpub/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/241120-polpub/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Efficiency: Operations as a Generator of Strategic Value</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/241119-claseejecutiva/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/241119-claseejecutiva/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimization and waiting lists</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/240814-cienciadedatos/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/240814-cienciadedatos/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algorithms in a hyperconnected world</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/240513-13c/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/240513-13c/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Opportunities and challenges of generative AI</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/230517-ey/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2023 09:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/230517-ey/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pauta de Negocios</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/221129-pauta/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2022 09:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/221129-pauta/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CNN Divergentes</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/220618-cnn/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 09:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/220618-cnn/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Todo por la Ciencia (in Spanish)</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/180302-t13/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Mar 2018 09:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/180302-t13/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
