<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Conferences and Science Communication | Homepage</title>
    <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.raxlab.science/talk/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Conferences and Science Communication</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Rodrigo A. Carrasco, 2025</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 10:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.raxlab.science/images/icon_hu5d34eb5e588cdfdf4e24081213af8ad4_29191_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Conferences and Science Communication</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leading with Evidence in Times of Uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/251007-emol/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/251007-emol/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This opinion column, published in &lt;em&gt;El Mercurio&lt;/em&gt;, argues that the &lt;strong&gt;value&lt;/strong&gt; of data work is realized in the prescriptive step: turning predictions into feasible actions under real-world constraints—“the predictive informs; the prescriptive decides.” It lays out what’s required to make that leap: rigorous data governance (quality, traceability, timeliness), explicit treatment of uncertainty (scenarios and robust optimization), short-cycle impact metrics, and decision governance (clear activation rules and explainability). Drawing on examples in health, environmental monitoring, and maintenance, it proposes a practical path: start from high-value problems, set honest baselines, formulate prescriptive models with actual constraints, pilot with counterfactual evaluation, and then institutionalize and scale.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;📰 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://ingenieriaindustrial.ing.uc.cl/blog/liderar-con-evidencia-en-tiempos-de-incertidumbre/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the article&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The RISE AI Conference</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/251008-rise/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Oct 2025 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/251008-rise/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Together with Paula Aguirre, VP of Digital Intelligence at UC Chile, we spoke at the inaugural &lt;strong&gt;RISE (Responsible, Inclusive, Safe &amp;amp; Ethical) AI Conference&lt;/strong&gt; at the University of Notre Dame (Oct 6–8, 2025), joining the panel &lt;strong&gt;“The Impact of AI in Latin America.”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussion focused on enabling &lt;em&gt;equitable&lt;/em&gt; AI ecosystems in the region: strengthening data governance and interoperability, building talent and research capacity, expanding access to compute and secure data environments, and advancing collaborative models that translate AI research into public-good applications (health, environment, cities). We emphasized responsible deployment—explainability, accountability, and robust evaluation—so AI systems improve outcomes without widening structural gaps.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Artificial City: Designing Future Scenarios through Data and AI</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250911-planeo/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Sep 2025 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250911-planeo/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;TIn this interview with &lt;em&gt;Revista PLANEO&lt;/em&gt;, I discuss how data science can inform urban decision-making under uncertainty, bridging descriptive, predictive, and prescriptive analytics, while stressing governance, institutional capacity, and ethics. We talk about translating complex models into actionable tools for public decision-makers, the need for data literacy and transparent communication, and the risk of widening gaps if only wealthy cities can leverage data. I argue for shared repositories and collaboration mechanisms so that smaller or vulnerable municipalities can benefit as well, advancing fairer and more sustainable urban management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The challenge is to prevent only the wealthiest cities from benefiting from the use of data… we need collaboration mechanisms and shared repositories…”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;📰 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://revistaplaneo.cl/2025/09/09/entrevista-a-rodrigo-carrasco-el-desafio-es-evitar-que-solo-las-ciudades-mas-ricas-puedan-beneficiarse-del-uso-de-datos-necesitamos-mecanismos-de-colaboracion-y-repositorios-compartidos-que-permit/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the interview&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>La Florida Hospital Triples Oncology Appointments through Use of Data Science</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250730-emol/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250730-emol/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This interview, published in &lt;em&gt;El Mercurio&lt;/em&gt;, highlights the results of an innovative pilot program that &lt;strong&gt;tripled oncology care capacity&lt;/strong&gt; at Hospital Dra. Eloísa Díaz de La Florida. The project combined &lt;strong&gt;data science&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;process redesign&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;natural language processing&lt;/strong&gt; to transform scattered patient data into structured information for clinical management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I discussed how our team—together with &lt;strong&gt;José Peña&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Jocelyn Dunstan&lt;/strong&gt;, and professionals from the Hospital de La Florida, developed a model that automates patient tracking, identifies care bottlenecks, and improves prioritization. By integrating data across systems, the pilot helped increase the number of patients managed from 900 to nearly 3,000 per care navigator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The initiative demonstrates how &lt;strong&gt;algorithmic tools can support, not replace, clinical judgment&lt;/strong&gt;, and how innovation, when designed with system constraints in mind, can have immediate and scalable impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;📰 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ing.uc.cl/wp-content/uploads/2025/07/6067186_4469944-scaled.jpg&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Read the article (image)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Radio Interview: Managing Cancer Patient Pathways through Data</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250728-biobio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Jul 2025 10:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250728-biobio/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;With &lt;strong&gt;José Peña&lt;/strong&gt; we were interviewed on &lt;strong&gt;Radio BioBio&lt;/strong&gt; to discuss our research on oncology patient management, carried out in collaboration with &lt;strong&gt;José Peña&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;Jocelyn Dunstan&lt;/strong&gt;. The conversation focused on how many cancer patients in Chile face fragmented care and long delays, and how we can use data science, natural language processing, and optimization tools to support more equitable and timely care pathways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We emphasized that patients should not have to navigate complex systems alone—and that we can use algorithmic tools not to replace human judgment, but to strengthen it. As I said during the interview: &lt;em&gt;“The goal is to put intelligence at the service of life.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;▶️ 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.instagram.com/reel/DMjGlCLIPAx/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Watch the summary clip on Instagram&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>13th International Conference on Mathematical Methods in Reliability</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250626-mmr/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250626-mmr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At &lt;strong&gt;MMR 2025&lt;/strong&gt;, our group contributed three presentations that reflect the breadth of our work at the intersection of data science, optimization, and maintenance engineering across diverse industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ignacio Riego&lt;/strong&gt; presented a data-driven solution for &lt;strong&gt;automated maintenance planning in the airline industry&lt;/strong&gt;, focusing on the creation of personalized maintenance checks. This work is part of our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FONDECYT project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, which explores optimization and analytics strategies to improve large-scale maintenance operations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Andrés Catalán&lt;/strong&gt; shared a novel method for &lt;strong&gt;log anomaly detection in distributed systems&lt;/strong&gt;. His talk introduced a transformer-based approach combining sentiment analysis and explainability to enhance detection in complex environments. This research is also embedded within the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FONDECYT project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, addressing predictive modeling in high-frequency operational contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Alejandro Maccawley and Ricardo Askenazy&lt;/strong&gt; presented a predictive model for &lt;strong&gt;equipment degradation in wine bottling lines&lt;/strong&gt;, using real-time sensor data to anticipate failures and optimize interventions. This work is part of the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2024plasma/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;PLASMA project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, a collaboration with Viña Concha y Toro focused on applying prescriptive maintenance tools in the food and beverage sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together, these talks demonstrate the versatility of our research group in applying cutting-edge analytical methods to real-world maintenance challenges, and the relevance of our 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/&#34;&gt;FONDECYT&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2024plasma/&#34;&gt;PLASMA&lt;/a&gt; initiatives in advancing applied research across industries.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Advancing Research through Integrated Scientific and Operational Data Management and Governance</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250618-pasc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250618-pasc/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Scientific field stations generate vast amounts of data, ranging from environmental measurements to operational logistics. However, the lack of structured data governance and integration strategies often hinders the full potential of these datasets, limiting their impact on research and decision-making. At Universidad Católica, we are developing a data platform designed to streamline the management, sharing, and utilization of scientific and operational data across the Regional Field Stations Network (RCER). This platform aims to provide researchers with reliable, well-organized, and accessible data by implementing robust governance models, standardized storage structures, and seamless cloud integration. By bridging scientific and operational data streams, we enhance reproducibility, data-driven decision-making, and interdisciplinary collaboration. A key component of this effort involves the development of local data management strategies that ensure field stations can efficiently capture and process their data before integrating with the broader system. In this presentation, we will discuss the challenges of scientific data governance in distributed field environments, the methodologies we are employing to create a scalable and sustainable data infrastructure, and the expected impact on research output. Through this initiative, we aim to empower scientists by unlocking the full potential of the data they generate, ultimately advancing research across multiple disciplines.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Joining prediction and optimization: prescriptive scenario generation for energy management with storage </title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250325-heidelberg/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2025 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250325-heidelberg/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the &lt;strong&gt;1st Heidelberg–Chile Workshop on Scientific Computing&lt;/strong&gt;, I presented our research on prescriptive scenario generation for energy management in microgrids with renewable generation and battery storage. The talk focused on bridging the gap between prediction and optimization by integrating forecasting methods and scenario-based stochastic programming into a unified decision-making framework.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We explored techniques for generating decision-aware scenarios using adaptive partitioning methods and highlighted the shift from a “predict-then-optimize” approach to a “predict-and-optimize” paradigm. Results from simulation studies in residential microgrids demonstrated significant gains in operational efficiency compared to conventional control strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work is part of the 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2020gema/&#34;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;GEMA project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, funded by FONDEF, and involves collaboration with colleagues and students across several institutions. The methods developed are currently being tested in real-world pilot implementations and cloud-based energy platforms.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When Time Is Life: Innovation for Oncology Waitlists in Chile</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250312-polpub/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250312-polpub/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;On March 12, 2025, I published an opinion piece in &lt;em&gt;El País&lt;/em&gt; titled &lt;em&gt;“When Time Is Life: Innovation for Oncology Waiting Lists in Chile.”&lt;/em&gt; The article discusses how data-driven innovation can transform oncology waitlist management, reducing delays and improving access to timely care. It highlights key strategies—such as digitalization, automation, and optimization—to enhance both efficiency and equity in the Chilean healthcare system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can read the full article here: 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://elpais.com/chile/2025-03-12/cuando-el-tiempo-es-vida-innovacion-para-las-listas-de-espera-oncologicas-en-chile.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;El País&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oncology Waitlist: Strategies for Management in Health Services</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/241120-polpub/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/241120-polpub/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Efficiency: Operations as a Generator of Strategic Value</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/241119-claseejecutiva/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/241119-claseejecutiva/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimization and waiting lists</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/240814-cienciadedatos/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/240814-cienciadedatos/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algorithms in a hyperconnected world</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/240513-13c/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/240513-13c/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Opportunities and challenges of generative AI</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/230517-ey/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2023 09:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/230517-ey/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pauta de Negocios</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/221129-pauta/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2022 09:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/221129-pauta/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CNN Divergentes</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/220618-cnn/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 09:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/220618-cnn/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interview at Radio Guayacán</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/220309-guayacan/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2022 18:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/220309-guayacan/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Michigan Center for Global Surgery Symposium</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/211105-umichigan/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2021 15:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/211105-umichigan/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimización matemática: conectando predicción y prescripción para mejores decisiones</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/211007-jornadadiiio/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Oct 2021 11:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/211007-jornadadiiio/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>National Engineering Day Web Seminar by Universidad Católica de Temuco</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/210513-uctemuco/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2021 15:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/210513-uctemuco/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Makers Fair Vina 2020.</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/201112-makersfair/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 16:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/201112-makersfair/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Martes de Física y Astronomía / Physics and Astronomy Tuesdays.</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/200714-uaiphysics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 19:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/200714-uaiphysics/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Viaje al Centro de los Datos / Voyage to the Center of Data.</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/200507-centrodatos/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 22:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/200507-centrodatos/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modelos de Decisión ante crisis / Decision models for a crisis.</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/200424-fic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 19:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/200424-fic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OPTIMA 2019</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/191125-optima/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 19:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/191125-optima/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Todo por la Ciencia (in Spanish)</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/180302-t13/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Mar 2018 09:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/180302-t13/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
