<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rodrigo A. Carrasco | Homepage</title>
    <link>https://www.raxlab.science/author/rodrigo-a.-carrasco/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.raxlab.science/author/rodrigo-a.-carrasco/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Rodrigo A. Carrasco</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Rodrigo A. Carrasco, 2025</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 08:30:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.raxlab.science/author/rodrigo-a.-carrasco/avatar_hu026587757f14f8b514635c55ac6745b9_60297_270x270_fill_q90_lanczos_center.jpg</url>
      <title>Rodrigo A. Carrasco</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/author/rodrigo-a.-carrasco/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>When Time Is Life: Innovation for Oncology Waitlists in Chile</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250312-polpub/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/250312-polpub/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enhanced Detection of Human-Driven Forest Alterations using Echo State Networks</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/couso-2024-edfa-neurips/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/couso-2024-edfa-neurips/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Oncology Waitlist: Strategies for Management in Health Services</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/241120-polpub/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2024 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/241120-polpub/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond Efficiency: Operations as a Generator of Strategic Value</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/241119-claseejecutiva/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2024 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/241119-claseejecutiva/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>PLASMA: Analytical Platform for Maintenance Systems</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2024plasma/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Oct 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2024plasma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The PLASMA project aims to enhance maintenance management in industrial settings by developing a cloud-based analytical platform that integrates advanced predictive and prescriptive algorithms. Initially designed for use in complex systems like the ALMA Radiotelescope, these algorithms will now be adapted and validated for broader industrial applications. The platform’s core focus is to predict equipment degradation and remaining useful life (RUL), allowing maintenance teams to preemptively address issues and optimize resource allocation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with Viña Concha y Toro, PLASMA will deploy its algorithms within bottling and packaging lines to minimize operational disruptions and reduce the costs associated with equipment downtime. The project involves a comprehensive analysis of sensor data and production metrics to calibrate the predictive models for accuracy in real-world scenarios. Alongside prediction capabilities, the platform will also support decision-making through stochastic optimization models that balance maintenance costs with equipment reliability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project’s end goal is a scalable, cloud-based platform capable of managing predictive maintenance across diverse industrial sectors. With the support of technology partner Orión, PLASMA will be designed for 24/7 digital support, providing a robust solution for maintenance planning and execution. By ensuring the flexibility to adapt to various industrial contexts, the platform has the potential to generate significant value by reducing operational costs and enhancing equipment availability across sectors like viticulture, mining, and manufacturing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is funded by FONDEF IT24I0031 grant from ANID, and supported by Concha y Toro and Orion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project Team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Director: Alejandro Mac Cawley&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subdirector: Rodrigo A. Carrasco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Researchers: Gonzalo Ruz, Margarita Castro, Anthony Cho&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimization and waiting lists</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/240814-cienciadedatos/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Aug 2024 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/240814-cienciadedatos/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Uncertainty estimation through quantile forest for prescriptive scheduling of data processing at ALMA</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2024-ueqf-spie/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2024-ueqf-spie/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algorithms in a hyperconnected world</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/240513-13c/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 May 2024 08:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/240513-13c/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is the change deforestation? Using time-series analysis of satellite data to disentangle deforestation from other forest degradation causes</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/fuentes-2024-forest-rsase/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/fuentes-2024-forest-rsase/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Development of Oncology Waiting List Prioritization Strategies</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/project/polpub2024onco/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2024 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/project/polpub2024onco/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project focuses on improving access to cancer care in Chile by developing prioritization models for oncology waiting lists within the South Eastern Metropolitan Health Service. Cancer remains one of the leading causes of mortality in Chile, and the existing lack of standardized prioritization criteria has led to extensive and uneven waiting lists, particularly impacting disadvantaged socioeconomic groups. By enhancing the way oncology patients are prioritized for systemic therapies, such as chemotherapy, this project seeks to improve equity and efficiency within the public health system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our approach leverages data science and mathematical optimization to develop robust models for managing these waiting lists. The research involves a detailed mapping of current scheduling and prioritization processes for oncology treatments, which serves as the case study foundation. We will also conduct a comprehensive review of prioritization models in similar contexts to inform our methodology. Data quality assessments will allow us to identify actionable insights, and data extraction techniques will be applied to build effective decision-support tools based on available health data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through this project, we aim to create a framework for dynamic prioritization that can be tailored to capacity limitations and patient needs, incorporating constraints such as guaranteed health coverage and specific cancer treatment requirements. Beyond oncology, the methodologies and models developed here hold the potential for application in other areas of healthcare, providing a scalable solution for optimizing resource allocation and patient care across diverse medical fields.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is funded by Políticas Públicas UC grant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project Team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Director: Rodrigo A. Carrasco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Researchers: Jocelyn Dunstan, José Peña&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Opportunities and challenges of generative AI</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/230517-ey/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2023 09:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/230517-ey/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resource cost-aware scheduling problems under uncertainty</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondecyt2023/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Our project addresses the critical balance between resource consumption and scheduling efficiency in settings where resources are limited or costly, such as astronomical observatories, manufacturing, and maintenance processes. Managing these constraints effectively can lead to substantial performance improvements but requires advanced techniques to weigh the trade-off between consuming resources and meeting scheduling demands. In many cases, resources, such as energy or workforce, are not only limited but also costly, adding an extra layer of complexity to scheduling tasks optimally.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A unique aspect of this research is its focus on scheduling under uncertainty, where key parameters, like job sizes or deadlines, may not be known beforehand. This complexity is particularly relevant to observatories in Chile, where variable factors such as sky quality or observation lengths affect task durations. Through collaboration with some of the largest observatories, we gain access to unique datasets and domain expertise, enabling us to test our methods in real-world scenarios. This approach also opens pathways to apply our findings in other industries that face similar scheduling and resource challenges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are developing a comprehensive set of prescriptive analytics tools, including new algorithms with strong theoretical guarantees and benchmarks that address these resource-cost-aware scheduling problems. Our work will involve constructing approximation algorithms using mathematical programming and resource augmentation techniques. We aim to build a publicly accessible repository of benchmark instances—using real-world data and factoring in uncertainties and various scheduling metrics—that will advance research in this field and provide robust, adaptable solutions for diverse applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is funded by FONDECYT 1231245 grant from ANID.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project Team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PI: Rodrigo A. Carrasco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Co-PI: Gonzalo Ruz&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Co-PI: Luis Aburto&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pauta de Negocios</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/221129-pauta/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2022 09:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/221129-pauta/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A RUL Estimation System from Clustered Run-to-Failure Degradation Signals</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/cho-2022-rul-sensors/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/cho-2022-rul-sensors/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>CNN Divergentes</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/220618-cnn/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jun 2022 09:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/220618-cnn/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Improving prescriptive maintenance by incorporating post-prognostic information through chance constraints</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/cho-2022-prmain-ieeeaccess/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/cho-2022-prmain-ieeeaccess/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dealing with Uncertain Surgery Times in Operating Room Scheduling</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2021-ors-ejor/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2021-ors-ejor/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interview at Radio Guayacán</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/220309-guayacan/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Mar 2022 18:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/220309-guayacan/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Michigan Center for Global Surgery Symposium</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/211105-umichigan/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2021 15:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/211105-umichigan/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimización matemática: conectando predicción y prescripción para mejores decisiones</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/211007-jornadadiiio/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Oct 2021 11:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/211007-jornadadiiio/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using smartphone photographs of the Moon to acquaint students with non-Euclidean geometry</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/caerols-2021-moon-ajp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/caerols-2021-moon-ajp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Operations Research Tools Applied to Observatory Operations </title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/project/obervatoryops/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Jul 2021 22:22:24 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/project/obervatoryops/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The problem of scheduling operations in astronomical observatories has been tackled in various ad-hoc ways. Although it is a central task in an observatory’s operation, which affects the utilization and throughput of observations, extensive manual intervention is still required in almost all observatories. Moreover, little resources have been invested in optimizing the scheduling’s efficiency, which, in the case of large-scale observatories like ALMA or VLT, might result in significant cost-effective improvements. This issue gains importance since observatory operations have increased in complexity, with plenty of sources of uncertainty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This issue has a lot in common with problems typically found in other industries. Operations research tools have been used here to develop solutions for many related topics, from scheduling production plans to routing delivery vehicles. These tools and methodologies have been a source of efficiency, allowing organizations to do more with limited resources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project aims to connect these two worlds, kickstarting and fostering interdisciplinary research between operations research and astronomy operations by tackling one of the most relevant problems: optimal operations scheduling. The focus will be to develop and apply operations research tools to construct decision support systems that can help managers improve efficiency and utilization.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is funded by grant ASTRO20-0058 from ANID and the Atacama Large Millimeter Array (ALMA) Radio Telescope.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project Team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lead Researcher: Rodrigo A. Carrasco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Associate Researchers: Andrés Jordán, Vincent Suc, Rafael Brahm&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engineers: Benjamín Bastidas, Constanza Lorca&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students: Looking for motivated students to work in this topic!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Equipo, sistema y método para administrar óptimamente la energía en una red de uso domiciliario e industrial</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2019-clpatent-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2019-clpatent-1/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>National Engineering Day Web Seminar by Universidad Católica de Temuco</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/210513-uctemuco/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 May 2021 15:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/210513-uctemuco/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ClimateDL: Forecasting of extreme temperature events</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/project/climat2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2021 22:22:24 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/project/climat2022/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Forecasting extreme seasonal temperature events is especially relevant to society and its ecosystem due to their potentially dangerous impacts. Despite the above, the study of this problem is still very nascent in South America, where most of the methods proposed in the literature correspond to process-based dynamic models and classical statistical methods. Increasing the accuracy of predicting the probability of occurrence of extreme temperatures at the seasonal scale would have huge impacts on our economic life (food production, energy consumption), health, etc.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Innovative approaches are emerging in climate forecasting, using network science and machine learning methodologies. The complex interrelations between temporal and spatial variables in climate time series justify the use of climate networks as an underlying automatic model explanation of the complex physical processes involved. The use of machine learning methods, particularly deep learning architectures, is justified by their success in several forecasting problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this project, we will evaluate the precision of the most prominent deep-learning architectures for our forecasting problem, particularly those implementing spatiotemporal models based on graphs (climate networks). The most promising antecedents for this methodology are several works based on climate networks and the effect of “El Niño” on similar forecasting problems. We expect to propose improvements to these deep learning architectures to increase their precision in our particular problems. For example, changing the scale of nodes, changing the similarity of edges, proposing new architectures that include multiple networks, training the model with augmented data, etc. We will implement and compare the results with classical statistical methods, such as principal component regression technique and Wavelet transform-based methods, among others. Assuming we achieve good predictive quality, we will evaluate the impact of these predictions on some human activities. We will focus on risk analysis of specific infrastructures (telecommunication networks, energy distribution) and on concrete case studies in situations where the considered extreme events have a strong negative impact and for which historical data are available.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is funded by grant 22-CLIMAT-02 (AMSUD210012) from ANID.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project Team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;International Project Coordinator: Pablo Rodríguez Bocca, Universidad de la República, Uruguay&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Country Coordinator (Chile): Rodrigo A. Carrasco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Country Coordinator (Argentina): Matilde Rusticucci, Universidad de Buenos Aires&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Country Coordinator (France): Yassine Hadjadj-Aoul, INRIA&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Researchers: (Argentina) Mariana Barrucand, Soledad Collazo, (Chile) Javiera Barrera, Eduardo Moreno, (France) Gerardo Rubino, Sebastián Basterrech, (Uruguay) Madeleine Renom, Diego Kiedanski.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Makers Fair Vina 2020.</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/201112-makersfair/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 12 Nov 2020 16:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/201112-makersfair/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Slow Degradation Fault Detection in a Harsh Environment</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/cho-2020-fdd-ieeeaccess/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/cho-2020-fdd-ieeeaccess/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Optimal decisions for salvage logging after wildfires</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/baselli-2020-odsl-omega/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/baselli-2020-odsl-omega/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Martes de Física y Astronomía / Physics and Astronomy Tuesdays.</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/200714-uaiphysics/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jul 2020 19:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/200714-uaiphysics/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>GEMS: variable-Generation Energy Management with Storage</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2020gema/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 22:25:44 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/project/fondef2020gema/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One of the exciting topics we&amp;rsquo;ve been working on is algorithms and models related to energy management, where uncertainty is a crucial element in the process. In particular, our focus is on building decision support tools for optimal storage management when a variable and intermittent energy source is used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project combines machine learning methodologies and stochastic optimization tools to develop optimal energy management systems for a system with photovoltaic generation, interconnection with the grid, and energy storage. If no storage is available, the decision is simple: if the generation is larger than our demand, we sell to the grid. Otherwise, we need to buy from the grid. However, when storage is present, the decision is more complex. Should we store the energy for future usage? Or maybe tomorrow, we will have a large surplus of energy that allows us to use the energy today, at a time when the price is high. When is the best time to sell, store, or use solar energy? We answer these questions through our research project by developing a prototype that implements the optimal decisions defined by our mathematical optimization models and measuring this approach&amp;rsquo;s benefits compared to today&amp;rsquo;s standard storage policies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project is funded by FONDEF ID19I10158 grant from ANID y has cloud resources thanks to the AWS Cloud Credit for Research program.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Project Team:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PI/Director: Rodrigo A. Carrasco&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Subdirector: Tito Homem-de-Mello&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Researchers: Francisco Jara, Jocelyn Olivari, Gonzalo Ruz, Carlos Silva&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Engineers: Benjamín Bastidas, José Luis Ortiz&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students: Anthony D. Cho, Helena García, César Cerda&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Prescriptive Maintenance</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/project/faultdetection/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 22:22:45 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/project/faultdetection/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project has two main lines of research. In one, we are developing tools to detect and diagnose faults in an automatic fashion. Using machine learning and mathematical modeling techniques, we are developing algorithms to help in online deteccion of faults at the ALMA Radiotelescope. In a second line, we are developing decision support tools, based on stochastic optimization, to develop robust maintenance plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This work is partially funded by FIE-2016-V022 and 16IFI6626 CORFO Grants.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Viaje al Centro de los Datos / Voyage to the Center of Data.</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/200507-centrodatos/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 May 2020 22:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/200507-centrodatos/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Real-time fleet management decision support system with security constraints</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/barrera-2020-rtfm-top/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/barrera-2020-rtfm-top/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modelos de Decisión ante crisis / Decision models for a crisis.</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/200424-fic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Apr 2020 19:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/200424-fic/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Operating room scheduling under waiting time constraints: the Chilean GES plan</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/barrera-2020-ors-aor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/barrera-2020-ors-aor/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>OPTIMA 2019</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/191125-optima/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Nov 2019 19:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/191125-optima/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Astronomical Scheduling in the Era of Big Observatories</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/toledo-2019-as-adass-17/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/toledo-2019-as-adass-17/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Salvage logging: harvest scheduling and personnel assignment after wildfires</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/baselli-2019-sl-bddss/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/baselli-2019-sl-bddss/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resource cost aware scheduling</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2018-rcas-ejor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2018-rcas-ejor/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>ALMA engineering fault detection framework</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/ortiz-2018-aedf-spie/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/ortiz-2018-aedf-spie/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Todo por la Ciencia (in Spanish)</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/180302-t13/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Mar 2018 09:30:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/180302-t13/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Server scheduling benchmark instances</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2018-bench-md/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2018-bench-md/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Demand shaping in an electrical power grid using day ahead market and real time market prices</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2014-uspatent-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2014-uspatent-2/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The online set aggregation problem</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2018-osa-latin/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2018-osa-latin/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Demand shaping in an electrical power grid</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2014-uspatent-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2014-uspatent-1/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Operating room scheduling with variable procedure times</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/azar-2017-ors-mapsp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/azar-2017-ors-mapsp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Proceedings of the XII Chilean conference on operations research</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2017-proc-optima/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2017-proc-optima/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Model-based fault detection and diagnosis in ALMA subsystems</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/ortiz-2016-mbfdd-spie/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/ortiz-2016-mbfdd-spie/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Single machine scheduling with job-dependent convex cost and arbitrary precedence constraints</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2013-sms-orl/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2013-sms-orl/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resource cost aware scheduling problems</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2013-ph-d-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2013-ph-d-thesis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robust electricity demand shaping through load shedding and shifting using day-ahead and real-time prices</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2013-reds-gls/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2013-reds-gls/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Single machine scheduling with job-dependent convex cost and arbitrary precedence constraints</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2013-sms-mapsp/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2013-sms-mapsp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fault detection and isolation in cooperative mobile robots using multilayer architecture and dynamic observers</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2011-fdi-robotica/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2011-fdi-robotica/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Energy aware scheduling: minimizing total energy cost and completion time by $α$-points and $α$-speeds</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2011-eas-mapsp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2011-eas-mapsp/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Layered architecture for fault detection and isolation in cooperative mobile robots</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2007-lafdi-ecc/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2007-lafdi-ecc/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nonlinear state estimation in mobile robots using a fuzzy observer</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2005-nse-ifac/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jan 2005 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2005-nse-ifac/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Detección y diagnóstico de fallas en robots móviles cooperativos</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2004-ms-thesis/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2004-ms-thesis/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fuzzy logic based nonlinear Kalman filter applied to mobile robots modelling</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2004-flkf-fuzz/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2004 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2004-flkf-fuzz/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Queen-bee genetic optimization of an heuristic based fuzzy control scheme for a mobile robot</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2003-qgo-lacra/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2003 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2003-qgo-lacra/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sistema de guiado para un robot móvil basado en lógica difusa</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2002-sg-acca/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2002 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/publication/carrasco-2002-sg-acca/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
