<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>webinar | Homepage</title>
    <link>https://www.raxlab.science/tag/webinar/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://www.raxlab.science/tag/webinar/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>webinar</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Rodrigo A. Carrasco, 2025</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 12:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://www.raxlab.science/images/icon_hu5d34eb5e588cdfdf4e24081213af8ad4_29191_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>webinar</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/tag/webinar/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transforming Technological and Digital Knowledge into Innovation in RTOs</title>
      <link>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/251126-waitro/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 12:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>https://www.raxlab.science/talk/251126-waitro/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;At the WAITRO LAC session on transforming technological and digital knowledge into innovation, we offered a two-part view from UC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, &lt;strong&gt;Nancy Rampaphorn&lt;/strong&gt; presented UC’s institutional framework for &lt;strong&gt;technology transfer&lt;/strong&gt;, showcasing the programs, agreements, and support services that translate research into innovation and partnerships with industry and the public sector.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, I presented &lt;strong&gt;SAVIIA&lt;/strong&gt;, UC’s trusted hybrid local–cloud platform that unifies RCER field-station data under clear governance (quality, traceability, timeliness). The focus was on local orchestration + cloud integration for reproducible pipelines that turn scientific and operational data into actionable, shareable research assets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key takeaways&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Governance-first data workflows (from capture to reuse) to ensure reliability and auditability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Local-to-cloud architecture enabling offline robustness and scalable analytics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;From datasets to decisions: reusable pipelines supporting collaboration across stations and teams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together, the talks connected &lt;strong&gt;data governance &amp;amp; transfer infrastructure&lt;/strong&gt; as the twin engines for moving evidence into innovation across RTOs.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
